So if you've been following the news,
حسناً، اذا كنتم تتابعون الاخبار
you've heard that there's a pack of giant asteroids
فقد سمعتم ان هناك حزمة من الكويكبات الكبيرة
headed for the United States,
متجهة نحو الولايات المتحدة
all scheduled to strike within the next 50 years.
من المتوقع ان تضرب في الخمسين عام القادمة
Now I don't mean actual asteroids made of rock and metal.
انا لا أعني كويكبات حقيقية من صخور و حديد
That actually wouldn't be such a problem,
بالعكس، هذه لن تكون مشكلة كبيرة
because if we were really all going to die,
لاننا لو كنا سنموت جميعاً من الكويكبات الصخرية
we would put aside our differences, we'd spend whatever it took,
فإننا اذاً سنضع اختلافاتنا بعيداً
and we'd find a way to deflect them.
و نبذل قصار جهدنا لنجد حل لإبعادها
I'm talking instead about threats that are headed our way,
و لكني في الحقيقة اتحدث عن الاخطار المتجهة نحونا
but they're wrapped in a special energy field
و هي ملفوفة في مجال طاقة معين
that polarizes us, and therefore paralyzes us.
يستقطبنا و بالتالي يشل حركتنا.
Last March, I went to the TED conference,
في مارس الماضي ذهبت الى مؤتمر تيد
and I saw Jim Hansen speak, the NASA scientist
ورأيت جيم هانسن العالم بوكالة ناسا يتحدث
who first raised the alarm about global warming in the 1980s,
يحذر من خطورة الاحتباس الحراري العالمي
and it seems that the predictions he made back then
و يبدو ان تنبؤاته في ذلك الوقت
are coming true.
تتحول الآن الى حقيقة.
This is where we're headed in terms of global temperature rises,
هذا هو اتجاه العالم من ارتفاع درجة الحرارة
and if we keep on going the way we're going,
و اذا بقينا نفعل ما نفعل
we get a four- or five-degree-Centigrade temperature rise
سنحصل على زيادة حرارية بمقدار ٤ الى ٥ درجات مئوية
by the end of this century.
في نهاية هذا القرن.
Hansen says we can expect about a five-meter rise in sea levels.
يقول هانسن انه يمكننا توقع زيادة ٥ امتار لارتفاع مستوى البحر
This is what a five-meter rise in sea levels would look like.
ارتفاع ٥ امتار من مستوى البحر يبدو هكذا.
Low-lying cities all around the world will disappear
كل المدن المنخفضة حول العالم ستختفي
within the lifetime of children born today.
في فترة حياة مواليد اليوم.
Hansen closed his talk by saying,
انهى هانسن كلامه بالقول:
"Imagine a giant asteroid on a collision course with Earth.
"تخيل ان هناك كويكب ضخم يضرب الارض"
That is the equivalent of what we face now.
"هذا هو حجم المشكلة التي نواجهها اليوم
Yet we dither, taking no action to deflect the asteroid,
و لكننا لا نزال نتردد، و لا نفعل اي شيء لإبعاد الخطر"
even though the longer we wait,
"رغم انه كلما تأخرنا
the more difficult and expensive it becomes."
كلما تعقدت المعضلة"
Of course, the left wants to take action,
بالتأكيد يريد اليساريين ان يفعلوا شيئا
but the right denies that there's any problem.
و لكن اليمينين ينكرون وجود اي مشكلة.
All right, so I go back from TED,
حسناً، عدت من مؤتمر تيد
and then the following week, I'm invited to a dinner party
و في الاسبوع التالي، كنت مدعواً الى حفلة عشاء
in Washington, D.C., where I know that I'll be meeting
في واشنطن دي سي، حيث اعرف انني سأقابل
a number of conservative intellectuals, including Yuval Levin,
عدد من المفكرين المتحفظين بمن فيهم (يوڤال ليڤن)
and to prepare for the meeting, I read this article by Levin
استعداداً للإجتماع قرأت مقال لـ يوڤان
in National Affairs called "Beyond the Welfare State."
في مجلة (ناشونال افيرز) بعنوان "بعيداً عن دولة الرعاية الاجتماعية"
Levin writes that all over the world,
يكتب ليڤن انه في جميع انحاء العالم
nations are coming to terms with the fact
الشعوب بدأت تكتشف ان دولة الرعاية الاجتماعية
is turning out to be untenable and unaffordable,
تبدو انها غير مجدية و مكلفة
dependent upon dubious economics
تعتمد على اقتصاد مشبوه
and the demographic model of a bygone era.
و نموذج ديموغرافي لعصر مضى.
All right, now this might not sound as scary as an asteroid,
حسناً، قد يبدو هذا اكثر رعباً من الكويكبات
but look at these graphs that Levin showed.
و لكن انظروا الى هذه الرسوم البيانية التي عرضها ليڤن
This graph shows the national debt
الرسم البياني يبين ان القرض القومي
as a percentage of America's GDP, and as you see,
كنسبة من إجمالي الناتج المحلي. و كما ترون،
if you go all the way back to the founding,
اذا رجعنا الى البدايات
we borrowed a lot of money to fight the Revolutionary War.
سنجد اننا اقترضنا الكثير من الاموال لخوض الحرب الثورية.
Wars are expensive. But then we'd pay it off, pay it off, pay it off,
الحروب مكلفة. و ثم نعود نسدد و نسدد و نسدد.
and then, oh, what's this? The Civil War. Even more expensive.
و بعد ذلك، اوه، ما هذا؟ الحرب الاهلية. اكثر تكلفة هذه المرة.
Borrow a lot of money, pay it off, pay it off, pay it off,
نقترض مالاً كثيراً، ثم نسدد و نسدد و نسدد.
get down to near zero, and bang! -- World War I.
نقارب من سداد كل الدين و من ثم فجأةً، الحرب العالمية الاولى.
Once again, the same process repeats.
و مرة أخرى، تعيد الكرّة نفسها.
Now then we get the Great Depression and World War II.
و بعدها يأتي الكساد الكبير و الحرب العالمية الثانية.
We rise to an astronomical level, around 118 percent of GDP,
و يرتفع الديْن الى مستويات قصوى.
really unsustainable, really dangerous.
١١٨ في المائة من إجمالي الناتج المحلي. خطر جداً و غير مستدام.
But we pay it off, pay it off, pay it off, and then, what's this?
و لكننا نسدده، و بعد ذلك، ما هذا؟
Why has it been rising since the '70s?
لماذا لم يتوقف عن الارتفاع منذ السبعينات؟
It's partly due to tax cuts that were unfunded,
جزئياً بسبب خصومات الضرائب التي لم تُشبَع.
but it's due primarily to the rise of entitlement spending,
و لكنها غالباً بسبب ارتفاع نفقة الاستحقاقات
especially Medicare.
بالذات الرعاية الطبية.
We're approaching the levels of indebtedness we had at World War II,
ها قد قاربنا ان نواجه ديْن الحرب العالمية الثانية
and the baby boomers haven't even retired yet,
و مواليد الخمسينات لم يتقاعدوا بعد
and when they do, this is what will happen.
و عندما يتقاعدوا، هذا ما سيحدث.
This is data from the Congressional Budget Office
هذه هي الارقام من مكتب الميزانية بالكونجرس
showing its most realistic forecast of what would happen
لترينا اقرب التوقعات لما قد يحدث
if current situations and expectations and trends are extended.
اذا استمرت الاوضاع و النمط الاقتصادي كما هو.
All right, now what you might notice is that these two graphs
حسناً، و الان قد تلاحظ ان هذان الرسمان البيانيان
are actually identical, not in terms of the x- and y-axes,
هما في الحقيقة متشابهان، ليس بالمحور x او y
or in terms of the data they present,
او حتى نوعية المعلومات التي يمثلاها
but in terms of their moral and political implications, they say the same thing.
و لكن من ناحية الانعكاسات السياسية و المعنوية، فهما يقولان نفس الشيء.
Let me translate for you.
دعني اترجم لكم كلامي
"We are doomed unless we start acting now.
"نحن في ورطة كبيرة اذا لم نفعل شيأً الآن
What's wrong with you people on the other side in the other party?
ماذا بكم يا ناس في الاحزاب الاخرى؟
Can't you see reality? If you won't help, then get the hell out of the way."
الا ترون الحقيقة؟ اذا لن تساعدوا، فأبتعدوا عن طريقنا."
We can deflect both of these asteroids.
يمكننا التأثير على هذان الكويكبان.
These problems are both technically solvable.
الحلول التقنية موجودة لهذه المشكلتان.
Our problem and our tragedy is that in these hyper-partisan times,
و لكن مشكلتنا الكبرى في زمن الحزبية المتشددة هذا
the mere fact that one side says, "Look, there's an asteroid,"
مجرد ان يقول احدهم "انظروا، هناك كويكب متجه نحونا"
means that the other side's going to say, "Huh? What?
يعني ان الطرف الاخر سيقول "هاه؟ ماذا؟"
No, I'm not even going to look up. No."
"لا، و لن انظر الى الاعلى اصلاً، لا"
To understand why this is happening to us,
لنفهم لما يحدث لنا هذا
and what we can do about it, we need to learn more about moral psychology.
و ماذا يمكننا ان نفعل بصدده، علينا ان نتعلم المزيد عن السايكولوجية المعنوية.
So I'm a social psychologist, and I study morality,
حسناً، انا سايكولوجي اجتماعي، و ادرس الاخلاقية او المعنوية
and one of the most important principles of morality
و احد أهم اعمدة العلوم المعنوية
is that morality binds and blinds.
هو ان المعنوية تربط و تُعمي
It binds us into teams that circle around sacred values
تربطنا في دوائر تدور حول قيم مقدسة
but thereby makes us go blind to objective reality.
و بالتالي تعمينا من الحقيقة الموضوعية.
Think of it like this.
فكر بها هكذا،
Large-scale cooperation is extremely rare on this planet.
التعاون ذو النطاق الواسع شيء نادر على هذا الكوكب.
There are only a few species that can do it.
هناك انواع معينة و قليلة تستطيع فعل ذلك.
That's a beehive. That's a termite mound, a giant termite mound.
هذه خلية نحل. و هذا تل للنمل الابيض.
And when you find this in other animals, it's always the same story.
و عندما تجد هذا في اي نوع اخر من المخلوقات، دائماً ستجد نفس القصة.
They're always all siblings who are children of a single queen,
دائماً يكونوا اخوة اطفال لملكة واحدة
so they're all in the same boat.
و كلهم في نفس السفينة.
They rise or fall, they live or die, as one.
يقومون و يقعون، يموتون و يحيون، سوياً.
There's only one species on the planet that can do this
هناك نوع واحد يمكنه فعل هذا من دون ملكية
without kinship, and that, of course, is us.
و هو بالطبع نحن.
This is a reconstruction of ancient Babylon,
هنا اعادة بناء لبابل القديمة
and this is Tenochtitlan.
و هذه تينوختيتلان.
Now how did we do this? How did we go
كيف فعلنا كل هذا؟
from being hunter-gatherers 10,000 years ago
كيف انتقلنا من صيادين من قبل عشر الف سنة
to building these gigantic cities in just a few thousand years?
الى بناء مدن ضخمة كهذه في بضع الف سنة؟
It's miraculous, and part of the explanation
انها معجزة، و جزء من السبب هو
is this ability to circle around sacred values.
قدرتنا على الدوران حول قيم مقدسة
As you see, temples and gods play a big role in all ancient civilizations.
و كما ترون، تلعب الالهة و المعابد دوراً كبير في كل الحضارات القديمة.
This is an image of Muslims circling the Kaaba in Mecca.
هذه صورة للمسلمون يدورون حول الكعبة بمكة.
It's a sacred rock, and when people circle something together,
هو حجر مقدس و عندما يدور الناس حول القيم سوياً
they unite, they can trust each other, they become one.
يتحدون، و تزداد ثقتهم ببعض و يصبحون واحد.
It's as though you're moving an electrical wire
كأنما تحرك سلك كهربائي
through a magnetic field that generates current.
عبر مجال مغنطيسي يولد طاقة.
When people circle together, they generate a current.
عندما يدور الناس سوياً يولدون طاقة.
We love to circle around things.
نحن نحب الدوران حول الاشياء.
We circle around flags, and then we can trust each other.
ندور حول الاعلام فنثق ببعضنا.
We can fight as a team, as a unit.
يمكننا عندها المحاربة في وحدة.
But even as morality binds people together into a unit,
و كما ان المعنويات تربط الناس سوياً في وحدة و فريق
into a team, the circling blinds them.
فهي ايضاً تعميهم
It causes them to distort reality.
و تشوه الحقيقة بالنسبة لهم.
We begin separating everything into good versus evil.
و نبدأ بتصنيف كل شيء في شكل خير و شر، جيد و سيئ.
Now that process feels great. It feels really satisfying.
هذه العملية مريحة جداً و تبعث بالرضى
But it is a gross distortion of reality.
و لكنها تشويه صريح للحقيقة.
You can see the moral electromagnet operating in the U.S. Congress.
يمكننا ان نرى الكهرومغناطيس الاخلاقي يعمل في الكونجرس الاميركي
This is a graph that shows the degree to which voting
هذا رسم بياني يوضح لأي درجة يقع
in Congress falls strictly along the left-right axis,
التصويت في الكونجرس بحدة حول المحور اليميني و اليساري
so that if you know how liberal or conservative someone is,
فإذا كنت تعرف درجة التحفظ او الليبرالية لأحد ما
you know exactly how they voted on all the major issues.
فأنت تعرف كيف صوتوا في كل الامور الكبرى
And what you can see is that,
و يمكنك ان ترى انه
in the decades after the Civil War,
في العقود ما بعد الحرب الاهلية
Congress was extraordinarily polarized,
كان الكونجرس في اقصى درجة من الاستقطاب
as you would expect, about as high as can be.
عالية جداً كما هو متوقع.
But then, after World War I, things dropped,
و لكن بعد الحرب العالمية الثانية، انخفضت الحدة
and we get this historically low level of polarization.
و حصلنا على اقل درجة استقطاب في التاريخ.
This was a golden age of bipartisanship,
كان هذا عصراً ذهبياً للتعاون،
at least in terms of the parties' ability to work together
على الاقل في قدرة الاحزاب للعمل سوياً
and solve grand national problems.
و حل المشكلات القومية.
But in the 1980s and '90s, the electromagnet turns back on.
و لكن في التسعينات و الثمانينات،
Polarization rises.
اندلع الكهرومغناطيس مرة اخرى و ازداد الاستقطاب.
It used to be that conservatives and moderates and liberals
كان يمكن للمتحفظين و الليبراليين و الوسطيين
could all work together in Congress.
ان يعملوا و يتعاملوا سوياً في الكونجرس
They could rearrange themselves, form bipartisan committees,
و تكوين لجان حزبية مشتركة
but as the moral electromagnet got cranked up,
و لكن مع ازدياد الكهرومغناطيس الاخلاقي
the force field increased,
اتسع مجال الطاقة
Democrats and Republicans were pulled apart.
فأبتعد الديمقراطيين من الجمهوريون
It became much harder for them to socialize,
و اصبح من الصعب عليهم ان يجتمعوا
much harder for them to cooperate.
و اصعب عليهم ان يتعاونوا
Retiring members nowadays say that it's become like gang warfare.
الاعضاء المتقاعدون يقولون انها مثل حرب العصابات
Did anybody notice that in two of the three debates,
هل لاحظتم ان في المناظرات الثلاث الاخيرة
Obama wore a blue tie and Romney wore a red tie?
كان اوباما يلبس ربطة عنق زرقاء و رومني يلبس ربطة عنق حمراء؟
Do you know why they do this?
هل تعرفون لما يفعلون ذلك؟
It's so that the Bloods and the Crips will know which side to vote for. (Laughter)
حتى يعرف عصابات (الكربز) و (البلدز) لمن يصوتون - (ضحك)
The polarization is strongest among our political elites.
فالاستقطاب عالي جداً لدى نخبة السياسيين
Nobody doubts that this is happening in Washington.
لا احد يشك بأن هذا يحدث في واشنطن.
But for a while, there was some doubt as to whether it was happening among the people.
و لكن لفترة كان هناك شك في اذا ما كان هذا يحدث بين الناس.
Well, in the last 12 years it's become
حقيقتاً، بدأ يحدث هذا في الـ١٢ عام الماضية
much more apparent that it is.
و اصبح اكثر وضوحاً.
So look at this data. This is from the American National Elections Survey.
انظروا الى هذه الارقام من مسح الانتخابات القومي الاميركي.
And what they do on that survey is they ask
و ما يفعلون في ذلك المسح هو ما يسمونه
what's called a feeling thermometer rating.
مقياس درجة حرارة الاحساس
So, how warm or cold do you feel about, you know,
بمعنى، بأي درجة من الدفئ او البرودة تشعر حيال
Native Americans, or the military, the Republican Party,
السكان الاصليين، او الجيش، الحزب الجمهوري
the Democratic Party, all sorts of groups in American life.
الحزب الديمقراطي، و كل انواع المجموعات في امريكا
The blue line shows how warmly Democrats feel
الخط الازرق يبين مدى دفئ شعور الديمقراطيين حول الديمقراطيين
about Democrats, and they like them.
و يحبونهم.
You know, ratings in the 70s on a 100-point scale.
كما تعلمون مقياس السبعينات، من درجة المئة.
Republicans like Republicans. That's not a surprise.
الدمقراطيون يحبون الديمقراطيون، هذه ليست بمفاجأة.
But when you look at cross-party ratings,
و لكن عندما ننظر الى مقياس الاحزاب المختلفة
you find, well, that it's lower, but actually,
ستجد انها اقل، و لكن في الحقيقة،
when I first saw this data, I was surprised.
عندما رأيت هذه الارقام لاول مرة، فوجئت.
That's actually not so bad. If you go back to the Carter and even Reagan administrations,
هذا ليس بسيئ. اذا عدنا الى رئاسة كارتر و ريجن
they were rating the other party 43, 45. It's not terrible.
كانو يصوتون للأحزاب الاخرى بـ٤٣ و ٤٥ ... ليس بسيئ.
It drifts downwards very slightly,
و تنزل الى الاسفل قليلاً
but now look what happens under George W. Bush and Obama.
و لكن، الان انظر ماذا يحدث تحت ادارة بوش و اوباما
It plummets. Something is going on here.
ترتفع درجة الاستقطاب بشكل فجائي.
The moral electromagnet is turning back on,
يبدو ان الكهرومغناطيس الاخلاقي بدأ بالعمل مرة اخرى،
and nowadays, just very recently,
و في هذه الايام، قريباً جداً
Democrats really dislike Republicans.
بدأ يبغض الديمقراطيين الجمهوريين
Republicans really dislike the Democrats. We're changing.
و الجمهوريين يبغضون الديمقراطيون. و نحن نتغير.
It's as though the moral electromagnet is affecting us too.
و كآنما الكهرومغناطيس الاخلاقي بدأ يأثر علينا نحن كذلك
It's like put out in the two oceans and it's pulling the whole country apart,
كأنما وضع في المحيطان و بدأ يقسم معه البلد
pulling left and right into their own territories
في جزئان، ايسر و ايمن
like the Bloods and the Crips.
مثل عصابات (البلدز) و (الكريبز)
Now, there are many reasons why this is happening to us,
و الان، هناك اسباب كثيرة لحدوث هذا
and many of them we cannot reverse.
و كثير منها لا يمكننا تغييرها.
We will never again have a political class
ابداً لن يكون هناك طبقة سياسية مزورة
that was forged by the experience of fighting together
بتجربة القتال سوياً ضد عدو مشترك
in World War II against a common enemy.
في الحرب العالمية الثانية.
We will never again have just three television networks,
ابداً لن يكون هناك فقط ٣ محطات تلفزيونية
all of which are relatively centrist.
جميعها مركزية.
And we will never again have a large group of conservative southern Democrats
و ابداً لن يكون هناك مجموعة كبيرة من المحافظين من الجنوب
and liberal northern Republicans making it easy,
و جمهوريين ليبراليين بالشمال يسهلون الامور
making there be a lot of overlap for bipartisan cooperation.
و فتح المجال للتعاون الحزبي.
So for a lot of reasons, those decades after the Second World War
و لذلك، لأسباب عدة، كانت تلك العقود بعد الحرب
were an historically anomalous time.
العالمية الثانية، اوقات تاريخية غريبة.
We will never get back to those low levels of polarization, I believe.
اعتقد اننا ابداً لن نعوذ لتلك الدرجات المنخفضة من الاستقطاب.
But there's a lot that we can do. There are dozens
و لكن هناك الكثير الذي يمكن فعله.
and dozens of reforms we can do that will make things better,
و الكثير من الاصلاحات الذي يمكن ان نفعلها لتحسين الاشياء
because a lot of our dysfunction can be traced directly
لأن الكثير من اسباب خمولنا يمكن ان تعرف و تدرس مباشرة
to things that Congress did to itself in the 1990s
و توصل بأشياء فعلها الكونجرس لنفسه في التسعينات
that created a much more polarized and dysfunctional institution.
و التي خلقت الكثير من الاستقطاب و المؤسسات الغير فعالة.
These changes are detailed in many books.
هذه التغييرات مفصلة في كتب عديدة
These are two that I strongly recommend,
و هذان اثتان منهم ارشحهم بقوة
and they list a whole bunch of reforms.
و يقومان بإدراج الكثير من اشكال الاصلاح.
I'm just going to group them into three broad classes here.
و انا سأقوم بتلخيصهم في ٣ فئات عريضة هنا.
So if you think about this as the problem of a dysfunctional,
اذا رأيتموها كمشكلة مؤسسة غير فعالة
hyper-polarized institution, well, the first step is,
بها درجة استقطاب عالية، اذا، فالخطوة الاولى هي:
do what you can so that fewer hyper-partisans get elected in the first place,
افعل ما بوسعك حتى يترشح القليل من المتشددين
and when you have closed party primaries,
و عندما تنتهي الانتخابات الاولية
and only the most committed Republicans and Democrats are voting,
و يصوتوا فقط الجمهوريين و الديمقراطيين الملتزمين
you're nominating and selecting the most extreme hyper-partisans.
تبدأ انت باختيار و ترشيح الحزبيين الاكثر تشدداً.
So open primaries would make that problem much, much less severe.
اذا فالانتخابات الاولية المفتوحة تخفف من حجم المشكلة بشكل كبير.
But the problem isn't primarily that we're electing bad people to Congress.
و لكن ليست المشكلة اننا نرشح اناساً سيئين في الكونجرس.
From my experience, and from what I've heard from Congressional insiders,
حسب خبرتي و بما سمعت من اشخاص داخل الكونجرس
most of the people going to Congress are good, hard-working,
فأغلب الناس الذين يعملون بالكونجرس هم اشخاص مثاليين و مجتهدين
intelligent people who really want to solve problems,
اذكياء حقاً يسعون لحل المشاكل
but once they get there, they find that they are forced
و لكن لمجرد وصولهم هناك، يُرغموا
to play a game that rewards hyper-partisanship
على ان يلعبوا اللعبة التي تكافئ الحزبية المتشددة
and that punishes independent thinking.
و تعاقب التفكير المستقل.
You step out of line, you get punished.
اذا خرجت عن الخطوط العريضة، تعاقب.
So there are a lot of reforms we could do
فهناك الكثير من الاصلاحات التي يمكننا فعلها
that will counteract this.
لتغير مجرى الاحداث.
For example, this "Citizens United" ruling is a disaster,
مثالاً، حكم "المواطنون المتحدون" هذا، كارثة
because it means there's like a money gun aimed at your head,
لانه يعني ان هناك مسدس مالي موجه نحوك
and if you step out of line, if you try to reach across the aisle,
و اذا خرجت عن الخط
there's a ton of money waiting to be given to your opponent
سيكون هناك الكثير من المال لخصمك
to make everybody think that you are a terrible person through negative advertising.
ليجعل الجميع يقف ضدك عن طريق الاعلام السلبي.
But the third class of reforms is that we've got to change
و لكن الفئة الثالثة من الاصلاحات هو اننا يجب علينا ان نغير
the nature of social relationships in Congress.
طبيعة العلاقات الاجتماعية في الكونجرس.
The politicians I've met are generally very extroverted,
السياسون الذين قابلتهم عامةَ اناس منفتحين
friendly, very socially skillful people,
صدوقين، و موهوبين اجتماعياً
and that's the nature of politics. You've got to make relationships,
و هذه طبيعة السياسة. يجب عليك ان تبني علاقات
make deals, you've got to cajole, please, flatter,
و اتفاقيات و صفقات، يجب عليك المجاملة، و تمدح
you've got to use your personal skills,
يجب عليك استخدام العلاقات الشخصية
and that's the way politics has always worked.
و هكذا هي السياسة منذ البداية.
But beginning in the 1990s, first the House of Representatives
و لكن في بداية التسعينات
changed its legislative calendar
غير مجلس النواب التقويم التشريعي
so that all business is basically done in the middle of the week.
بحيث ان تنجز كل الاعمال في منتصف الاسبوع
Nowadays, Congressmen fly in on Tuesday morning,
اليوم، يصلون اعضاء الكونجرس صباح الثلاثاء
they do battle for two days, then they fly home Thursday afternoon.
يعملون لمدة يومان، و يعودون الى منازلهم ظهر الخميس.
They don't move their families to the District.
فهم لا يرحلون عوائلهم معهم الى المنطقة
They don't meet each other's spouses or children.
و لا يقابلون زوجات و ابناء بعضهم البعض
There's no more relationship there.
و تموت الروابط الاجتماعية بينهم.
And trying to run Congress without human relationships
و تشغيل الكونجرس من غير علاقات انسانية
is like trying to run a car without motor oil.
مثل تشغيل سيارة من غير زيت ماكينة.
Should we be surprised when the whole thing freezes up
اذا لما نتفاجأ اذا تجمدت الامور
and descends into paralysis and polarization?
و اصبحت مشلولة و مستقطبة؟
A simple change to the legislative calendar,
تغيير بسيط في تقويم التشريع
such as having business stretch out for three weeks
بحيث ان يمتد العمل لمدة ٣ اسابيع
and then they get a week off to go home,
و من ثم اجازة اسبوع يذهبون فيها الى ديارهم،
that would change the fundamental relationships in Congress.
سيغير هذا طبيعة العلاقات في الكونجرس
So there's a lot we can do, but who's going to push them to do it?
فيبدو ان هناك الكثير الذي يمكننا فعله و لكن من سيدفعهم لفعل هذا؟
There are a number of groups that are working on this.
هناك عدد من المجموعات التي تعمل بهذا الصدد
No Labels and Common Cause, I think,
"نو ليبلز" : بغير تسمية و "كومون كوز": قضية مشتركة
have very good ideas for changes we need to do
لديهم افكار جيدة للتغييرات التي نحتاجها
to make our democracy more responsive and our Congress more effective.
لنجعل ديمقراطيتنا مجيية و الكونجرس اكثر فعالية.
But I'd like to supplement their work
و لكني اود ان الحق عملهم
with a little psychological trick, and the trick is this.
بلفتة سايكولوجية صغير، و هذه اللفتة انه
Nothing pulls people together like a common threat
لا شيء يوحد الناس اكثر من الخطر المهدد للجميع
or a common attack, especially an attack from a foreign enemy,
و بالذات الخطر القادم من عدو غريب
unless of course that threat hits on our polarized psychology,
بالطبع مالم، يعرف هذا الخطر او (العدو) سر ضعفنا و استقطابنا.
in which case, as I said before, it can actually pull us apart.
في تلك الحالة كما قلت من قبل، يمكنه ان يقسمنا الى اجزاء
Sometimes a single threat can polarize us, as we saw.
و احياناً خطر واحد يستطيع استقطابنا كما رأينا
But what if the situation we face is not a single threat
و لكن ماذا لو كان الخطر الذي نواجهه ليس واحداً فقط
but is actually more like this,
و لكن كان هكذا،
where there's just so much stuff coming in,
حيث ان هناك الكثير من المخاطر الدخيلة
it's just, "Start shooting, come on, everybody,
"ابدأوا بالهجوم يا جماعة"
we've got to just work together, just start shooting."
"لنعمل سوياً، فقط هجوم هجوم"
Because actually, we do face this situation.
لانه في الحقيقة، نحن نواجه نفس المشكلة
This is where we are as a country.
و هذا ما نحن عليه كشعب.
So here's another asteroid.
و ها هو كويكب آخر،
We've all seen versions of this graph, right,
جميعنا رأينا صيغ أخرى لهذا الرسم البياني، صحيح
which shows the changes in wealth since 1979,
و هو يوضح التغيير في مستوى الثروات من ١٩٧٩
and as you can see, almost all the gains in wealth
و كما ترون، تقريباً كل الزيادات في الثروة
have gone to the top 20 percent, and especially the top one percent.
ذهبت الى الـ ٢٠ بالمئة من الطبقة العليا و بالذات الواحد في المئة
Rising inequality like this is associated
صعود اللا مساواة هكذا يرتبط
with so many problems for a democracy.
مع مشاكل للديمقراطية
Especially, it destroys our ability to trust each other,
و بالذات انها تدمر ثقتنا ببعض و اننا في نفس السفينة،
to feel that we're all in the same boat, because it's obvious we're not.
و من الواضح انه ليس كذلك.
Some of us are sitting there safe and sound in gigantic private yachts.
بعضنا يجلس على ياخت خاص كبير و آمن
Other people are clinging to a piece of driftwood.
و البعض الاخر يتمسك بلوح خشب.
We're not all in the same boat, and that means
نحن لسنا على متن نفس السفينة، و هذا يعني
nobody's willing to sacrifice for the common good.
انه ليس من يريد التضحية للفائدة المشتركة.
The left has been screaming about this asteroid for 30 years now,
صرخ اليساريون بخصوص هذا الكويكب لـ٣٠ عاماً حتى الان
and the right says, "Huh, what? Hmm? No problem. No problem."
و يقول اليمينيين "هاه؟ ماذا؟ همم؟ لا من مشكلة"
Now,
و الآن،
why is that happening to us? Why is the inequality rising?
ماذا يحدث لنا، لماذا تتصاعد هذه اللا مساواة؟
Well, one of the largest causes, after globalization,
حسناً، احد اكبر المسببات، بعد العولمة،
is actually this fourth asteroid,
هو في الحقيقة، الكويكب الرابع،
rising non-marital births.
صعود نسبة المواليد خارج الزواج.
This graph shows the steady rise of out-of-wedlock births
هذا البيان يوضح الصعود المستمر لمواليد خارج الزواج
since the 1960s.
منذ الستينات.
Most Hispanic and black children are now born to unmarried mothers.
معظم اطفال الهسبانو و الافارقة يولدون اليوم لأمهات غير متزوجات
Whites are headed that way too.
و البيض لاحقون في هذا الطريق كذلك.
Within a decade or two, most American children
في غضون عقد او اثنين، معظم الاطفال الاميركيين
will be born into homes with no father.
سيولدون في بيوت من غير أب
This means that there's much less money coming into the house.
و هذا يعني ان هناك دخل اقل في المنزل.
But it's not just money. It's also stability versus chaos.
و لكنه ليس قفط المال، بل ايضاً عدم الاستقرار و الفوضى.
As I know from working with street children in Brazil,
على حسب خبرة عملي مع الاطفال المتشردين في البرازيل
Mom's boyfriend is often a really, really dangerous person for kids.
صديق الام في الاغلب يكون مشكلة كبيرة جداً جداً على الاطفال.
Now the right has been screaming about this asteroid since the 1960s,
و صرخ اليمينيين بخصوص هذا الكويكب منذ الستينات
and the left has been saying, "It's not a problem. It's not a problem."
و يقول اليساريين "لا مشكلة لا مشكلة"
The left has been very reluctant to say
يتردد اليساريون في القول
that marriage is actually good for women and for children.
ان الزواج صحي و مفيد للأطفال و النساء
Now let me be clear. I'm not blaming the women here.
و لكني دعني اوضح، انا لا الوم النساء ها هنا
I'm actually more critical of the men
في الحقيقة، انا اكثر نقداً للرجال
who won't take responsibility for their own children
الذين لا يتحملون مسؤولية ابنائهم
and of an economic system that makes it difficult
و الاقتصاد الذي يجعل من الامر اكثر صعوبة
for many men to earn enough money to support those children.
للكثر من الرجال لجني ما يكفي من المال لرعاية هؤلاء الاطفال.
But even if you blame nobody, it still is a national problem,
و لكن حتى لو لم نلم احد، تظل هي مشكلة وطنية
and one side has been more concerned about it than the other.
و احد الاطراف مهتم اكثر من غيره
The New York Times finally noticed this asteroid
و النيو يورك تايمز اخيراً رصدت هذا الكويكب
with a front-page story last July
مع خبر في اول صفحة في يوليو الماضي
showing how the decline of marriage contributes to inequality.
يرينا كيف يساعد انحطاط مستوى الزواج على اللا مساواة.
We are becoming a nation of just two classes.
اصبحنا شعباً بطبقتين فقط.
When Americans go to college and marry each other,
عندما يذهب الاميركيين الى الجامعة و يتزوجون من بعضهم البعض
they have very low divorce rates.
لديهم معدل منخفض في نسبة الطلاق
They earn a lot of money, they invest that money in their kids,
يجنون مالاً كثيراً و يستثمرون ذلك المال في اطفالهم
some of them become tiger mothers,
و بعضهن يصبحن امهات قويات
the kids rise to their full potential,
الأبناء يصلون لإمكانياتهم القصوى
and the kids go on to become
و يمضي الابناء ليصبحوا
the top two lines in this graph.
في الخطوط العليا لهذا الرسم البياني.
And then there's everybody else:
و من ثم هناك الباقين:
the children who don't benefit from a stable marriage,
الاطفال الذين لا ينتفعون من الزواج المستقر
who don't have as much invested in them,
و الذين لم يُستثمر فيهم كثيراً،
who don't grow up in a stable environment,
و لا ينمون في بيئة مستقرة
and who go on to become the bottom three lines in that graph.
و الذين يمضون ليصبحوا في الثلاث خطوط السفلية لهذا الرسم البياني
So once again, we see that these two graphs are actually saying the same thing.
مرة اخرى نرى ان هذان الرسمان في الحقيقة يقولان نفس الشيء
As before, we've got a problem, we've got to start working on this,
و كما فعلنا في السابق، يجب ان نبدأ بحل المشكلة
we've got to do something,
علينا ان نفعل شيء
and what's wrong with you people that you don't see my threat?
و ماذا بكم يا ناس لا ترون الخطر؟
But if everybody could just take off their partisan blinders,
و لكن لو استطاع الناس ان يخلعوا حواجزهم الحزبية،
we'd see that these two problems actually
سنرى ان هاتان المشكلتان، في الحقيقة
are best addressed together.
يمكن النظر اليهم سوياً.
Because if you really care about income inequality,
لأنك اذا كنت تهتم بخصوص مساواة الدخل
you might want to talk to some evangelical Christian groups
فقد تريد ان تكلم بعض الجماعات الانجيلية المسيحية
that are working on ways to promote marriage.
التي تعمل في الدعاية الى الزواج
But then you're going to run smack into the problem
و لكنك ستواجه المشكلة الاخرى
that women don't generally want to marry someone
و هي ان النساء لا يريدون الزواج من احد
who doesn't have a job.
لا يملك وظيفة.
So if you really care about strengthening families,
فإذا كنت تهتم بتقوية الأُسرة
you might want to talk to some liberal groups
تحدث مع الجماعات الليبرالية
who are working on promoting educational equality,
الذين يدعون الى المساواة في التعليم
who are working on raising the minimum wage,
و الذين يعملون لزيادة الدخل المحدود
who are working on finding ways to stop so many men
و هم يعملون لايجاد طرق لايقاف الكثير من الرجال
from being sucked into the criminal justice system and
من الوقوع في نظام الجريمة و العدالة
taken out of the marriage market for their whole lives.
و الابتعاد من سوق الزواج مدى الحياة.
So to conclude, there are at least four asteroids headed our way.
في الملخص، هناك ٤ كويكبات متجهة نحونا.
How many of you can see all four?
من منكم يراهم كلهم؟
Please raise your hand right now if you're willing to admit
ارفعوا ايديكم الآن اذا كنتم تنوون الاعتراف
that all four of these are national problems.
بأن هؤلاء الأربعة هم مشاكل قومية.
Please raise your hands.
ارفعو ايديكم رجاءً.
Okay, almost all of you.
حسناً، غالبيتكم.
Well, congratulations, you guys are the inaugural members
اذاً، مبروك، انتم الاعضاء الافتتاحيين
of the Asteroids Club, which is a club
لنادي الكويكبات، و هو نادي
for all Americans who are willing to admit
لكل الامريكيين الذين يعترفون
that the other side actually might have a point.
ان الفريق الاخر قد يكون على صواب
In the Asteroids Club, we don't start by looking for common ground.
في نادي الكويكبات لا نبدأ بالبحث عن ارضية مشتركة
Common ground is often very hard to find.
الارضية المشتركة من الصعب ان نجدها
No, we start by looking for common threats
لا، سنبدأ بالبحث عن خطر مشترك
because common threats make common ground.
لأن الخطر المشترك يصنع الارضية المشتركة.
Now, am I being naive? Is it naive to think
الآن، هل انا ساذجاً بعض الشيء؟ اهو من الساذج الاعتقاد
that people could ever lay down their swords,
انه يمكن للناس ان يضعوا سيوفهم
and left and right could actually work together?
و اليمين و اليسار يمكن ان يعملوا سوياً؟
I don't think so, because it happens,
لا اعتقد ذلك، لأن هذا يحدث
not all that often, but there are a variety of examples that point the way.
ليس كثيراً، و لكن هناك الكثير من الامثلة التي تشير
This is something we can do.
الى انه شيء يمكن فعله.
Because Americans on both sides care about the decline in civility,
لأن الاميركيين في الطرفين، يهمهم امر التمدن
and they've formed dozens of organizations,
و قد كونوا الكثير من المنظمات
at the national level, such as this one,
على المستوى القومي، مثل هذه
down to many local organizations,
و كذلك المنظمات المحلية
such as To The Village Square in Tallahassee, Florida,
مثال "تو ذا فلج سكوير" في تلاهاسي، فلوريدا
which tries to bring state leaders together to help facilitate
و هي تحاول ان تأتي بقدوة الولاية ليساعدو
that sort of working together human relationship
في تسهيل هذا النوع من العمل الانساني و الجماعي
that's necessary to solve Florida's problems.
و الذي هو عامل مهم في حل مشاكل فلوريدا
Americans on both sides care about global poverty and AIDS,
اميركا من الطرفين تهتم بالفقر و الايدز
and on so many humanitarian issues,
و الكثير من المشاكل الانسانية
liberals and evangelicals are actually natural allies,
اللبراليين و الانجيليين في الحقيقة هم حليفان بالطبيعة
and at times they really have worked together
و في احيان كثيرة عملوا سوياً
to solve these problems.
ليحلوا هذه المشاكل
And most surprisingly to me, they sometimes can even see
و المفاجئ بالنسبة لي، انهم احياناً يرون الامور من
eye to eye on criminal justice.
نفس الزاوية بخصوص العدالة و الجريمة.
For example, the incarceration rate, the prison population
مثالاً، معدل الحبس، فعدد سكان السجون
in this country has quadrupled since 1980.
في هذا البلد تربع منذ ١٩٨٠
Now this is a social disaster,
و هذه كارثة اجتماعية.
and liberals are very concerned about this.
و الليبراليين كثيري الاهتمام بذلك.
The Southern Poverty Law Center is often fighting
المركز القانوني للفقر بالجنوب دائماً ما يحارب
the prison-industrial complex, fighting to prevent a system
مجمع السجن الصناعي، لمنع نظام يمتص المزيد و المزيد من الشباب
But are conservatives happy about this?
و لكن هل المتحفظون سعيدين لهذا العمل؟
Well, Grover Norquist isn't, because this system
جروفر نوركست غير راض عن ذلك، لآن هذا النظام
costs an unbelievable amount of money.
يكلف مبالغ خيالية.
And so, because the prison-industrial complex
و لذلك، لأن مجمع السجن الصناعي يفلس
is bankrupting our states and corroding our souls,
ولاياتنا و يقمع ارواحنا
groups of fiscal conservatives and Christian conservatives
جماعات التحفظ المالي و المتحفظين المسيحيين
have come together to form a group called Right on Crime.
اتو مع بعضهم لتكوين مجموعة تسمى (حق على الجريمة)
And at times they have worked with the Southern Poverty Law Center
و في بعض الاحيان عملوا مع المركزالقانوني للفقر بالجنوب
to oppose the building of new prisons
لمعارضة بناء السجون الجديدة
and to work for reforms that will make the justice system
و لعمل اصلاحات من شأنها ان تجعل نظام الجريمة و العدالة
more efficient and more humane.
اكثر كفائة و انسانية.
So this is possible. We can do it.
اذاً هذا يمكن، و يمكننا فعله.
Let us therefore go to battle stations,
لنخرج الى محطات المعركة
not to fight each other,
ليس لنحارب بعضنا البعض
but to begin deflecting these incoming asteroids.
و لكن لنبدأ بردع هذه الكويكبات القادمة
And let our first mission be to press Congress
و نجعل اول مهامنا ان يتغير الكونجرس من الداخل
to reform itself, before it's too late for our nation.
قبل فوات الاوان لشعبنا
Thank you. (Applause)
و شكراً. (تصفيق)